Sony just made their biggest change in history.
From 2028, there will be no more
physical PlayStation games.
Everything will be digital.
No more secondhand, no more sharing games,
everything will be through the Sony store.
And it’s backfiring.
But according to Sony,
this is just where customers are moving.
So, are they right? Is this really
just where things are moving?
And, why are physical games still so important?
Let’s take a closer look at what’s
really happening, and Sony’s claims.
In the official blog post, they say “As consumer
preferences and the broader entertainment industry
continue to shift away from physical discs to
digital, physical game disc production for all new
games releasing on PlayStation consoles will be
discontinued starting January 2028. Following this
date, new games will be available on PlayStation
Store and at retailers in digital formats only.”
This is a first in PlayStation history.
This also seems to heavily imply,
the PS6 won’t have a disc drive. So
no more Blu-ray or DVD support either.
Immediately, after this announcement went
live, the backlash was widespread, and intense.
66 thousand likes, over 100 thousand replies,
70 thousand retweets. Almost twice the
amount of replies to likes, is a bad sign.
“You will own nothing”. 122 thousand likes.
“#NOTBUYINGPS6 unless it supports physical games.”
“Guys, this is a really bad decision. Wtf.”
“I have no words, final nail in the
coffin of the company I once loved.”
This news began spreading everywhere.
Retailers, understandably, weren’t very happy.
“Shall we start with PS+ cancellations for today?”
Which, for the record, people did.
Other brands began mocking Sony’s announcement.
“In response to trends in the gaming industry,
Domino’s will cease production of physical pizzas
and shift to production of digital pizzas only”.
KFC did the same.
Some of these were pretty funny.
“In response to the gaming industry removing
physical offerings, [Proton] have decided
to make our services entirely physical.”
It wasn’t just Sony getting flack either.
They get paid to promote
upcoming games with posts on X.
But even the games affiliated with Sony,
after the announcement, received
huge backlash, and review bombs.
What makes all of this even more ironic,
is that Sony made fun of Xbox for doing
this same thing, except 13 years ago.
Boy does this ad have a lot more attention today.
“This video has aged just as well as Netflix's
"Love is sharing a password" tweet”
“Play does have LIMITS after all.”
But, this ad shows us how Sony have changed.
This is Shuhei Yoshida and Adam Boyes. The
former President of Sony Worldwide Studios and
former VP of Third-Party / Publisher & Developer
Relations, and was heavily involved
in some of the biggest Sony titles.
But Yoshida was actually fired, because he
disagreed with PlayStation CEO Jim Ryan.
“Jim Ryan wanted to remove me from first-party
because I didn't listen to him. He asked to do
some ridiculous things, and I said 'No.'”
The point about first party developers,
is very interesting, because it’s
not just consumers who are upset.
Industry veterans and long-time Sony partners, are
expressing that they’re not thrilled about this.
Hideo Kojima, one of the most acclaimed
video game directors in history, said
[Hideo Kojima]: Since production is ending in
2028, this is about video games, but I grew
up with physical media, so I find it really
sad. They are downloaded to the hard drive,
that means the game data remains on your own
hardware. However, if things shift to streaming
in the future, that won’t be the case anymore.
There are companies that own these servers and
let you 'turn the tap' for a monthly fee.
However, one naturally has to consider the
possibility that if there is a change, the
data inside will stop being distributed.
And if that happens you won’t be able to
watch or play the movies and games you like.
But, something about all of this is a bit weird.
On July 3, two days after the announcement,
Sony CEO Hiroki Totoki sold 56%
of his SONY shares for $4.7M.
On the same day, Chairman Kenichiro
Yoshida sold 400,000 shares,
and other Sony executives sold too.
The combined insider sales are
roughly around $10.5 million.
Granted, this is related to a
Sony buyback. But the timing sure is strange.
But, despite all the backlash… is Sony wrong?
Is this just the uncomfortable
truth, that physical games are dying?
Sony said “consumer preferences and the broader
entertainment industry continue to shift away from
physical discs to digital”. So, are they right?
Tension
According to Sony, 78% of games sold
for the full year of 2025, were digital.
But in Q4 digital downloads for full games
was 85% of sales, while physical was just 15%.
But, that’s just Sony, and there’s
something else to consider.
On the PS store are hundreds of games, many
of which never make it to physical media,
because their market is so small anyway. It’s the
bigger games that have wider, physical releases.
Since Sony is including everything, this
will be naturally skewed more digital.
A heavy-hitting physical game, like
God of War, will be counted the same
as a 99 cent game on the PS store.
But, only 7 games have sold over
100,000 physical units for the financial year.
Which makes it clear how small the library of
physical games is on the PS5, compared
to the PS4, which had a vast library.
Though, even the biggest physical releases
were heavily skewed towards digital. FC 26,
aka the new name for the FIFA series, had
physical sales of just 12%. Not only that,
6.4 million didn’t even buy the game, at all,
but played it through the PS Plus subscription.
Other games had a larger physical
split, but not too much more.
Resident Evil Requiem, 3.5 million sales,
about 28% physical, Crimson Desert,
1.9 million, about 20% physical.
And this gets a bit more bleak when
we look at the actual financials.
According to their financial results for
2025, physical software, aka physical games,
was 121 billion yen. Digital
software was 949 billion yen.
But, let’s look a bit further, beyond Sony.
According to the UK digital entertainment
and retail association, 89.5% of games
sold in the UK, were digital downloads.
Though note, this includes mobile apps,
though that only made up 30% of sales.
It seems, to be honest, pretty cut and dry.
Physical, is without a doubt,
becoming more niche for video games.
Though, there is one hole in Sony’s argument.
You can buy a regular PS5, or a digital-only
version, which has no disc drive.
“Not only does the company charge less
for the digital-only PS5, but the new
PS5 Pro only comes in a digital version.”
Yet, 82% of all PS5s have a disc drive.
Even though it’s more expensive, and
even though most sales are digital.
That tells you something
about what customers want.
They still value having
both, and will pay for both.
So, why is Sony doing this… really.
It turns out, it’s because
of “consumer preferences”.
If you’ve watched this far, you probably enjoy
our stuff, so consider subscribing! Thanks.
Rhys Elliott, from Alinea
Analytics made an excellent point,
about something Sony is really fighting.
[Rhys Elliott, Alinea Analytics]: “Our estimates
have 25%, almost 900K players of Resident Evil
Requiem’s PS5 player base clocking under 10 hours.
What I’m getting at here is that plenty
of those physical copies will end up in
the hands of resellers, which is exactly
what neither Capcom nor PlayStation wants.”
The beauty of physical products, is
that you can sell them, loan them,
or give them away when you’re done.
But, every time someone does this,
it means Sony misses out on revenue.
The reality is, Sony aren’t doing this
because of “consumer trends”. They’re doing
this, to improve margins, gain sales that are
taken by second hand copies.
This is all about margins.
With the move away from physical disc, no
more second hand games bought and sold,
no more sharing games.
You can’t even buy a console
second hand with games, because they’re
attached to the account, not the console.
Everything you buy will be under Sony’s
thumb, and they can do whatever they want.
They just removed over 500 movies from the
PlayStation store as licenses expire. Even if
you bought some of these, you can’t watch them
anymore. And they can do this with games too.
In fact, they just did in
August, removing 9 from PS Plus.
Also, under their terms, if you
haven’t used your account in 3 years,
they’ll just close your account, and you’ll lose
permanent access to all products you paid for.
As a reminder, people pay over $600 for
one of these consoles. Imagine doing that,
and paying hundreds more for digital
products, and Sony removes them all.
And if you don’t believe me, game
companies are already doing this.
In 2024 Ubisoft, another game publisher, delisted
the open-world multiplayer racing game “The Crew”.
They then shut the game servers
down, meaning nobody could play
it anymore, because it’s “always online”.
Customers had paid full price for this game,
and had also purchased microtransactions.
[Ubisoft]: "We understand this may be
disappointing for players still enjoying the game,
but it has become a necessity due to upcoming
server infrastructure and licensing constraints.”
Customers were, understandably, quite
annoyed, which led to a lawsuit.
Ubisoft argued that there was no reason
for players to believe they were purchasing
“unfettered ownership rights in the game.”
This is why the “Stop Killing Games”
movement has gained so much support in the EU.
Even if people don’t buy physical games as much,
they still like the option to be able to.
Hence the massive proportion of disc-drive PS5s.
Sony is just taking away choice from consumers.
Choice that other companies… hopefully…
will continue to offer. Which
makes the PS5 less appealing.
One of the best feelings, is playing an
old, favourite game, or movie from 10,
20, or even 30 years ago, because
you still have the physical disc.
No need to worry about licenses expiring, accounts
being removed, online support disappearing.
Push it in and play, because it’s your
property, which you exchanged money for.
The scariest part, about all of this,
is that it might be a thing of the past.
You won’t be able to share games, or sell them, or
trade them in. They’ll be locked to one account,
which is at the mercy of Sony.
If their license ends, gone. If
you get banned, even for a false reason, gone.
Sony can’t take your physical products from you,
but they can do whatever they
want with your digital ones.
[Hideo Kojima, 2021]: “Eventually, even digital
data will no longer be owned by individuals on
their own initiative. Whenever there is
a major change or accident in the world,
in a country, in a government, in an idea, in
a trend, access to it may suddenly be cut off.”
But there’s another major
problem with digital games.
Physical prices fluctuate with supply and demand,
but for Digital, Sony controls
the store, and the price.
They can also determine what price
you pay, vs what your friend pays.
And recently, people discovered
a massive experiment, where Sony
quietly did exactly this. (Also show this).
Click here to learn the rest of the story.